Guide to the John Prentice Allen Papers 1918-1992
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
John Prentice Allen Papers
1918-1992
1930s-1970s
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Allen, John Prentice
WCMss.351
10 linear feet 9 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes
The John Prentice Allen Paper, which date from 1930 to 1979, contains correspondence, travel brochures and concert programs, work-related records, and documents relating to military service.
Collection is open for research.
Donated to the Whitman College and Northwest Archives between 1985 and 1992 by John P. Allen. The accession number associated with this donation is Retro-0759.
John Prentice Allen was born November 26, 1918, in Seattle, Washington to Rudolph and Anna Farrar Allen. He attended schools in Seattle and Aberdeen, Washington and graduated from Roosevelt High School in Seattle in 1936. He attended Whitman College, the University of Hawaii at Honolulu, the University of Colorado at Boulder, and the University of Kentucky at Lexington. He was a clerical worker at Whitman College from 1946 to 1950. He received a bachelor's degree from the University of Washington, and in 1952 received a master's degree in librarianship from the University of Washington. John also served during World War II in the U.S. Navy as a Japanese language officer. He was a librarian at Central Washington University in Ellensburg between 1952 and 1965, when he moved to Washington State University. He retired in 1981. He was a co-owner of the Hilltop Restaurant and Motel at Pullman. He died June 25, 1991.
The John Prentice Allen Papers includes correspondence between John and his parents and friends, and material describing travel and entertainment experiences. This collection, which dates from 1930 through 1979, also holds records of his career in library administration, genealogical materials relating to his family, and Japanese language materials relating to his service in the U.S. Navy during World War II.
Allen, Rudolph Gregory; Allen, Anna Farrar
Whitman College
Librarians; World War, 1939-1945
- Correspondence, 1932-1989; Series 1
  The majority of this series is correspondence between Allen and his parents, Rudolph and Anna.
  - Letters from Allen's mother Anna "Muddie" Farrar Allen, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Allen's mother Anna "Muddie" Farrar Allen, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes two letters Allen wrote to his parents in 1934
  - Letters from Allen's mother Anna "Muddie" Farrar Allen, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Allen's mother Anna "Muddie" Farrar Allen, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Allen's father Rudolph Allen, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Allen's friend "Fritz" from Germany, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence from relatives, circa 1932-1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence from family and friends, circa 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with mother, Anna Allen, 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters from mother, Anna Allen, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters from mother, Anna Allen, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters from mother, Anna Allen, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Family correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, family and friends, circa 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Family and friends, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Family correspondence, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Family correspondence, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence between Allen and Whitman College and some academic documents, circa 1941-1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Family correspondence, 1952-1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to employment, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with friends and associates, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Rudolph Allen correspondence, 1959-1969 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Family correspondence and postcards (3 folders), circa 1960s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence re: Allen bequest to Whitman College, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - ACLU correspondence, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Get well cards for Rudolph Allen following an accident (2 folders), 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence with parents and friends, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence between Allen and friends, Various (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence received by Allen during illness, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, circa 1945-1949 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Holiday greeting cards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook of post cards, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence between John Allen and parents, 1945-1949 (Box 10, Folder 36)
- Educational and employment materials, 1919-1965; Series 2
  Materials relating to John Allen's educational career, including high school and college yearbooks and a draft of his master thesis from the University of Washington. Records from his library career at Central Washington State and Washington State Universities are included.
  - Seattle Public Schools Special Certificate in Music, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Seattle Public Library Vacation Reading Club, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificates of Advancement in schools and report cards, circa 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cradle roll certificates Seattle First Baptist Sunday School, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Roosevelt High School graduation announcement, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Roosevelt High School yearbooks, 1933-1936 (Box 5)
  - The Hyakem, Central Washington College of Education yearbooks, 1956-1958 (Box 5)
  - The Hyakem, Central Washington University yearbooks, 1958, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Draft of Allen's Master of Librarianship thesis, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bibliography of Lectures delivered at Oxford University, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "The Introduction and Development of Writing in Japan", a paper by John P. Allen, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - University of Washington Library School materials (3 folders), circa 1952 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Diplomas from University of Washington, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Colorado University Sigma Chi information, 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Seattle public school records, 1932-1936 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - U. of Washington library program documents and employment letters, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Application for Rhodes Scholarship, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Travel and entertainment materials, 1906-1982; Series 3
  Travel brochures, concert programs, events, scrapbooks of travel
  - Concert program Central Washington College of Education, January 29, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Central Washington College Commencement programs, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Travel brochures and receipts, Various (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ellensburg sports car rally, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Map of Alaska (Alaska Steamship Company), Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Musical and theatre programs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Concert and theatre programs, circa 1930s-1940sUndated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Church service programs, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Travel tickets and receipts, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Ship passenger rate sheets, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Lions Club Quartet scrapbook of Rudolph Allen, circa 1926 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Enchanters Quartet photographs and publicity (Rudolph Allen), 1929 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Chinese restaurant menu, Undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - John Allen passport and travel information, circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Travel itinerary and brochures, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Travel log, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Travel itinerary and brochures, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Personal items, family memorabilia, and genealogical materials, 1857-1990; Series 4
  - Ancestors and descendants of Benjamin Gregory and Abigail Starr Sanford, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Service award American Red Cross (Mrs. Rudolph Gregory Allen), Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pencil drawing of nude, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bill receipts, Various (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Musical score books, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Simplified Swedish Grammar by Edwin Vickner, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Genealogical chart showing ancestry of Anna Clough Farrar, Undated (Box 1)
  - Financial records, bank, investments, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Expense ledger, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, random, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Two photographs of Allen; Librarians of CES, 1936, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of membership Longfellow Society, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - University of Washington academic papers, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Income and tax information, 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Music manuscripts, circa 1932 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Here and There in United States History, by John Dukes McKee, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    United States map.
  - Ellensburg Telephone Co. receipts, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Postcards, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - National Bank of Washington statements, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Stenotype instruction materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Boy Scout First Aid Kit, Undated (Box 5)
  - Two boxes matchbook collection and miscellaneous collectibles, Undated (Box 5)
  - Copy of New York Herald (Lincoln assassination), April 15, 1865 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Copy of New York Chronicle, October 17, 1857 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Milwaukee Monthly Magazine, July 1874 and November 1874 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Little Corporal, vol. XX, no.2, February 1875 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Rudolph Allen obituary, memorial book and other memorabilia of Hawaii trip, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Pullman mayor re property dispute, March 15, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Central Washington State College library correspondence (3 files), circa 1950-1960s (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
  - American Civil Liberties Union celebration program, December 12, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Hugh Johnson's Pocket Encyclopedia of Wine, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - The Oxford Self-Pronouncing Bible (gift to John Allen in 1935), 1897 (Box 6)
  - Holy Bible (S.S. Teacher's edition) - Inscribed to Mary J. Clough, 1891 (Box 6)
  - Manuscript - "The Destiny of Personality" by Allan Alden McRea, 1921 (Box 6)
  - Since Spindletop: A Human story of Gulf's first half-century by Craig Thompson, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Graduation and wedding announcements, Various (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Papers relating to the estate of Anna Allen, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Memorial service for Anna Allen, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Roosevelt High School 50th reunion files, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - John P. Allen retirement documents, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - S.W. Willard & Co. re: postage stamp collection, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Rudolph Allen certificate for service, May 17, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Genealogical chart - Clough and Farrar families, Society of Colonial Dames, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Anna Farrar Allen diaries, journals, correspondence, and travel brochures, Various (Box 8)
  - Rotary Club Pictorial History, University District, Seattle, 1939-1968 (Box 9)
  - Daily Reminder, 1943 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence re: Allen's bequest to Whitman College, February 15-17, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Baby book of John Allen including photo with mother, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Documents pertaining to sale of property in Kittitas County, Washington, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Marriage certificate, invitation to wedding of Anna Farrar and Rudolph Allen, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Marriage certificate of John P. Farrar and Florence B. Clough, 1890 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - World War I medallion and other keepsakes of Anna Farrar "Muddie" Allen, Undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Small box with announcements of John Allen's birth and congratulatory cards, 1918 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous diaries of Allen and Farrar families, Various (Box 10)
  - J.P. Farrar passport (in small box), Undated (Box 10)
  - Ledger book of investment transactions, Undated (Box 10)
  - Two framed photographs of John P. Allen in military dress, circa 1940s (Box 10)
  - Inventory of Rudolph Allen's art work, Undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Highlights of European Beer Industry" by Quentin J. Talbot (manuscript), May 12, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Slide rule, Undated (Box 10)
  - Post Cards and envelopes (empty) probably saved for Allen's stamp hobby, Various (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "A Tribute to Mother" pamphlet by F.D. van Amburgh (contains photos of John Allen's mother "Muddie", 1923 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Holiday greeting cards, Various (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Boy Scout and Cub Scout badges, circa 1930s (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Map and addresses of movie star homes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Birthday and other greeting cards, Various (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Sympathy notes and cards upon the death of Rudolph Allen, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Banking records, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Honda 450 motorcycle owners manual, Undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Anna Farrar "My Commencement" memorabilia from school in Colorado, circa 1900 (Box 12)
  - Pocket-size books: Book of Common Prayer, Japanese-English dictionaries, New Testament, "The Fairy Album", Undated (Box 12)
  - Biographical sketch of Bradley Tillinghast and other family genealogical materials of Anna Farrar Allen. (2 folders), Undated (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - "Stuff and Junk" collected by J.P.A., humorous limericks and poems, Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Calling cards and various forms of identification, Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Certified copies of birth certificate John P. Allen, November 26, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Telegrams, circa 1950 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Mutual Life Insurance Co. correspondence, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Papers regarding purchase of 1940 Chevrolet, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Musical programs and newspaper clippings, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - University National Bank records, circa 1950 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Snapshots of John Allen, circa 1940s (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - University of Washington Daily newspaper, May 2, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Social Security receipts, 1937-1940 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Insurance documents, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of construction project at University of Washington, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Jokes and humorous stories, Undated (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Descriptive depictions of sexual intercourse, Undated (Box 10, Folder 28)
- Materials related to employment, business, and military service, 1940-1980; Series 5
  Some material included in this series is foreign language material relating to Allen's work in the military translating Japanese.
  - Naval communication bulletin, January 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kaigun Tokuhon (The Navy Reader), circa 1940 (Box 2)
  - Japanese Military and Technical Terms pamphlets, circa 1940 (Box 2)
  - Gleanings from the Book of Books, by Alfred Irving Ludlow, translated into Korean, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lessons in Shoso (Japanese language text), 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Three spiral notebooks (appear to be shorthand), Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Navy materials (maps, language studies), circa 1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Three Japanese vocabulary books, circa 1940 (Box 5)
  - Humorous work-related materials, circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Hilltop Development Corporation Documents (2 folders), circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Internal memos and personnel correspondence, WSU library (multiple folders), circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Newspaper article from Pullman, WA on WSU faculty collective bargaining plan, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - John P. Allen employment documents, Various (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - John Allen military papers (Navy), circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Employment memos and correspondence at Whitman College, 1946-1950 (Box 10, Folder 10)